{"tossups": [{"question": "During this battle, one side\u2019s lack of rations prompted Kurt von Zeitzler to begin starving himself as a sign of solidarity. One side took advantage of this battle to launch the Little Saturn attack plan and target Rostov. This battle culminated with Operation Uranus, which led to the encirclement of the Sixth Army and the eventual surrender of Friedrich Paulus. For the point, name this 1942 battle on the Volga that is cited as the Eastern Front\u2019s turning point.", "answer": "Battle of<b> Stalingrad</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "The original draft sequence of the Neanderthal genome project used remains found in this country\u2019s Vindijia Cave. An ancient culture discovered in this country produced a clay dove sculpture that is found on the back of its 20 kuna note; that culture, the Vucedol inhabited areas like Vukovar. The Neolithic Danilo culture primarily lived in what is now this country\u2019s portion of the Dalmatian Coast. For the point, name this country where prehistoric sites have been found near Zagreb.", "answer": "<b> Croatia</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {}, {}, {"question": "Henry Wadsworth Longfellow wrote the poem \u201cChristmas Bells\u201d after his son was injured in a battle fighting for a unit named after this body of water. Irvin McDowell lost the First Battle of Bull Run, which was fought in two counties along this river; that battle involved a unit named for this river that later fought in the Peninsula Campaign under George McClellan. A Union \u201cArmy\u201d was named after, for the point, what river that flows through Washington D.C?", "answer": "<b> Potomac</b> River", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man promised to act on the findings of the Beveridge Report and campaigned on the slogan \u201clet us face the future.\u201d Before a controversial budget proposed by Hugh Gaitskell forced this man to resign, he negotiated the end of the occupation of Mandatory Palestine. This man established the National Health Service after winning a shock victory in the 1945 general election. For the point, name this Labour leader who succeeded Winston Churchill and thus attended the Potsdam Conference in his place.", "answer": "Clement<b> Attlee</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "After renovating Trier as ruler of the West, this leader won the Battle of Chrysopolis against Licinius, a man he had earlier ruled with as part of the Tetrarchy. This man used a tub of boiling water to kill his wife Fausta. During a civil war with Maxentius, this man, inspired by a vision of the letters chi [kye] and rho in the sky, won the Battle of Milvian Bridge. The Edict of Milan was signed by, for the point, what Roman emperor who renamed Byzantium after himself?", "answer": "<b> Constantine</b> the Great (accept<b> Constantine</b> I)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "This man founded the Simplified Spelling Board in an attempt to make English easier to learn. A close friendship with Thomas Scott gave this man the resources to set up his first enterprise, the Keystone Bridge Company. This man argued that the rich had a responsibility to engage in philanthropy in<em> The</em> <em>Gospel of Wealth</em>. After using the Bessemer process to dominate the industry, this man was bought out by JP Morgan in 1901. For the point, name this Scottish-American steel magnate.", "answer": "Andrew<b> Carnegie</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Uniquely, this religion reveres its scripture as its final and eternal prophet and leader; that text is called the Granth Sahib. Langar halls attached to this religion\u2019s Gurdwara temples provide free food to their community. For the point, name this Indian religion whose followers often take the last name Singh and follow the Five Ks.", "answer": "<b> Sikh</b>ism Page 2", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "This leader\u2019s foreign relations with China were defended in the White Paper by Secretary of State Dean Acheson. NSC-68, which was drafted under this President\u2019s State Department, argued for rollback instead of detente or containment of the Soviet Union. The United States entered into NATO under this president, who appointed Matthew Ridgway to replace Douglas MacArthur after disputes in military strategy. For the point, name this president who oversaw the start of the Korean War and the end of World War II.", "answer": "Harry S.<b> Truman</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A philosopher from this island proposed love and strife as additions to the four classical elements. The philosopher Empedocles legendarily died by throwing himself into a volcano on this island. Another philosopher was killed on this island after allegedly telling a Roman soldier \u201cdo not disturb my circles.\u201dArchimedes died on, for the point, what Mediterranean island during the siege of Syracuse?", "answer": "<b> Sicily</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "A Native American attack in what is now this state destroyed Henricus in 1622. Much of the land that became this state was originally controlled by the Powhatan Confederacy. A Native American was claimed as the ancestor of many of this state\u2019s \u201cFirst Families\u201d through Thomas Rolfe, son of John Rolfe and the Powhatan Pocahontas. For the point, name this first enduring English colony in the New World, now a state with historical sites at Williamsburg and Jamestown.", "answer": "<b> Virginia</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This war included the Battle of the Chinese Farm, where Ariel Sharon\u2019s troops attempted to defend a bridge crossing. After this conflict began with the surprise attack Operation Badr, Henry Kissinger conducted \u201cshuttle diplomacy\u201d to secure a ceasefire. The Camp David Accords brought an end to this conflict with Egypt and Syria. For the point, name this conflict in which Israel was attacked on the Day of Atonement.", "answer": "<b> Yom Kippur</b> War (accept<b> Ramadan</b> War; accept<b> October</b> War; accept<b> 1973 Arab-Israeli </b>War)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This man\u2019s raiding of Darien resulted in the capture of 20 tons of gold and silver during an attack on Nombre de Dios. On another expedition, this man left a bronze plaque to claim the San Francisco Bay area after landing in New Albion. This man boasted of \u201csingeing the beard of the king of Spain\u201d after he successfully launched a raid on Cadiz. For the point, name this English captain of the<em> Golden Hind</em> who completed the second circumnavigation of the globe and fought the Spanish Armada.", "answer": "Sir Francis<b> Drake</b> Page 3", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This event ended plans to create the agricultural empire of New Helvetia. This event was publicized by Samuel Brannan, who ran down streets shouting the news about it. A dry goods business was operated by Levi Strauss during this event, which began after John Marshall made a discovery at Sutter\u2019s Mill. The\u201c49ers\u201d raced to, for the point, what economic boon in which miners flocked to Sacramento to find riches?", "answer": "<b> California Gold Rush</b> (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was forced out of a window by his lover Manuela Saenz to avoid assassins in the September Conspiracy.<em> Peninsulares</em> who opposed this man were subject to murder after this man issued the \u201cDecree of War to the Death\u201d during the Admirable Campaign. This man attended the Guayaquil Conference with Jose de San Martin after engineering a victory at Boyaca to secure independence from Spain. For the point, name this general, known as the \u201cLiberator\u201d of South America.", "answer": "Simon<b> Bolivar</b> (or Simon Jose Antonio de la Santisima Trinidad<b> Bolivar</b> Palacios Ponte y Blanco) Page 4", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "This figure is the subject of a ballet commissioned by Lincoln Kirstein that opens and closes with\u201copen\u201d harmonies in the woodwind section in the \u201cOpen Prairie\u201d theme. Other sections of that ballet about this figure include \u201cMexican Dance,\u201d \u201cCard Game,\u201d and a movement depicting his death at the hands of Sheriff Pat Garrett. One of Aaron Copland\u2019s most well known ballets depicts, for the point, what Wild West outlaw who was shot and killed in 1881 at age 21?", "answer": "<b> Billy the Kid</b> (or Henry<b> McCarty</b>; accept William \u201cBilly\u201d<b> Bonney</b>)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "This event was investigated after senator Robert LaFollette had his office ransacked. A court case arising from this event,<em> McGrain v. Daugherty</em>, established Congress\u2019 right to compel testimony. This event marked the first time a Cabinet member went to jail after Albert Fall was arrested. Naval oil fields were leased for low rates in exchange for bribes during, for the point, what 1923 scandal that ravaged Warren G. Harding\u2019s presidency?", "answer": "<b> Teapot Dome</b> scandal", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This company hired Ellen Church as a \u201csky-girl\u201d to reduce the public\u2019s fear of flying. William Boeing helped create this company, which lost a DC-7 in a collision with a TWA plane over the Grand Canyon in 1956. This airline, which merged with Continental in 2010, was the victim of two terrorist attacks on 9/11, including Flight 93, which crashed in Pennsylvania. For the point, name this airline that has a hub at Chicago\u2019s O\u2019Hare International Airport and is the third largest airline in the world, behind American and Delta.", "answer": "<b> United</b> Airlines Incorporated (accept<b> Boeing Air Transport</b> before \u201cBoeing\u201d is mentioned)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This event was partially prompted after the tribunes Marullus and Flavus were sacked for daring to remove a laurel wreath, outraging civilians. This event was avenged during the Liberators\u2019 Civil War, in which the Battle of Philippi led to the suicide of the perpetrator Cassius. The target of this event had been stopped near Pompey\u2019s Theater and stabbed 23 times by a group led by Brutus. For the point, name this 44 BC attack on the Ides of March against a Roman ruler.", "answer": "<b> assassination</b> (or<b> murder</b>,<b> stabbing</b>, etc.) of Gaius<b> Julius Caesar</b> (prompt on partial answers)", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "While working in this state, Pinkerton agent Charles Siringo escaped an angry mob of miners by sawing a hole in the floor of his house and digging his way to safety; that took place during an 1892 strike that broke out in this state\u2019s city of Coeur d\u2019Alene. William Borah was from this state, whose capital is named for a fort established along the Snake River. For the point, name this state where an old railroad depot was converted into a potato museum in Blackfoot, east of Boise.", "answer": "<b> Idaho</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man organized the car bombing of diplomat Orlando Letelier on the streets of Washington D.C. The Caravan of Death began executing political prisoners under this man\u2019s regime, and his DINA secret police spearheaded Operation Condor to purge left-wing elements in his country. This man came to power with CIA aid after his predecessor attempted to nationalize the copper industry. For the point, name this successor of Salvador Allende, a dictator of Chile.", "answer": "Augusto<b> Pinochet</b> Page 6", "metadata": "History - World History"}], "bonuses": []}